Gabriele Ara, Eng

Embedded Systems, Real-Time Systems, System Programming, Research

☑ gabriele.ara@santannapisa.it ⋒ www.gabrieleara.it

© Livorno, Italy

Gabriele Ara is a Ph.D. Student at Scuola Superiore Sant'Anna, Pisa (Italy). He has more than 10 years of experience in system programming.

Gabriele's expertise spans multiple fields in Computer and Software Engineering and IT, including embedded systems, real-time systems, scheduling, computer architectures, software design and implementation, system programming, networking, and research.

He is currently a proud member of the Real-Time Systems Lab at Scuola Superiore Sant'Anna under the supervision of Prof. Tommaso Cucinotta, and his research interests include energy-aware scheduling of real-time systems on embedded platforms running Linux, high-performance network communications in cloud environments, and the simulation of multi-core real-time systems.

Gabriele has a B.Sc. in Computer Engineering (cum laude) from the University of Pisa, Pisa (Italy), and an M.Sc. in Embedded Computing Systems Engineering (cum laude), a course jointly offered by the University of Pisa and Scuola Superiore Sant'Anna, Pisa (Italy).

Gabriele speaks fluently Italian and English (almost) alike. His colleagues describe him as analytical, creative, competitive, and goal-oriented.

Current Position

Ph.D. Student, Scuola Superiore Sant'Anna, Pisa (Italy)

2019-Present

Supervisor: Prof. Tommaso Cucinotta

Research topics include Energy-Aware Scheduling of Real-Time Tasks, Dynamic Voltage and Frequency Scaling (DVFS) on Embedded Platforms, Real-Time Systems Simulation and Scheduling, and High-Performance Networking Stacks and Frameworks.

Experience

Textbook Author, Zanichelli editore S.p.A (Italy)

2013-Present

Gabriele writes from time to time chapters and sections of IT textbooks in Italian. The chapters focus on mobile application development essentials for Android OS, from the very basics to more advanced use-case examples.

High School Teaching Professional

2018-2019

Istituto di Istruzione Superiore "Vespucci-Colombo", Livorno (Italy)

For one academic year, Gabriele worked as a part-time professor in an Italian high school, teaching IT and IT Laboratory to both 10th and 11th-grade students.

E-learning Technical Specialist, University of Pisa, Pisa (Italy)

2017-2018

To support my studies, I worked a couple of years as on-site support to technical and teaching personnel for the University for practical aspects of live streaming classes and conferences and the post-production of videos of an e-learning platform. Duties included managing recording equipment, streaming software, and providing hands-on support in case of live failures.

Tutor, Independent Contractor, Livorno (Italy)

2013-2018

Throughout my university years, I managed to help some high school students in STEM fields as their tutor, helping them with assignments in classes such as Computer Engineering, IT, Maths, Electronics, and Physics.

Awards

Best Paper Award

2020

Gabriele Ara, Tommaso Cucinotta, Luca Abeni, Carlo Vitucci, for the work "Comparative Evaluation of Kernel Bypass Mechanisms for High-performance Inter-container Communications" at the 10th International Conference on Cloud Computing and Services Science (CLOSER), 2020

Education

Master of Science (M.Sc.) in Embedded Computing Systems University of Pisa and Scuola Superiore Sant'Anna, Pisa (Italy)	2019
Bachelor of Science (B.Sc.) in Computer Engineering University of Pisa, Pisa (Italy)	2016
Secondary Diploma as IT Professional Istituto Tecnico Industriale Statale G. Galilei, Livorno (Italy)	2013

Supervision

Leonardo Lai 2019

Master student in Embedded Computing Systems, Scuola Superiore Sant'Anna, Pisa (Italy)
Subject of the dissertation: Implementation and Evaluation of High-Performance Userspace Networking
Mechanisms for Virtualized Network Functions

Professional Skills

Communication skills Comfortable interacting with people with cross-cultural backgrounds from around the world. Gave presentations to moderate international audiences for conferences and workshops. Can communicate strengths and weaknesses of his work.

Organisational/Managerial skills Can both work in small teams and manage to get things done by himself. Comfortable leading other people when necessary to organize the work. Excellent debugging and investigative skills for software/computer systems.

Job-related skills

Following is the list of known programming languages and tools organized by proficiency level.

Excellent knowledge and proficiency:

• **C/C++**, including the understanding of language internals, standard libraries, POSIX, Linux-specific libraries, Linux system programming, microcontrollers programming.

Proficient knowledge:

- Virtualization technologies, including Docker, LXC, LXD, and custom solutions based on cgroups and namespaces:
- High-Performance Networking frameworks, including DPDK, FD.io VPP, Open vSwitch;
- Linux management and administrative tools for machine configuration and troubleshooting.
- Unix-based systems command line, scripting in Sh and Bash;
- · Java (standard libraries, JavaFX, Spring, Apache and Servlet libraries);
- Android App programming (using Java+XML);

Good knowledge:

- · Linux kernel internals and hacking;
- · JavaScript (standard libraries, JQuery, D3);
- Matlab and Simulink for scripting, data analysis, and system control or simulation;
- Web development using HTML5, PHP5, CSS3, XML, JSON, REST patterns;
- **SQL** and MySQL software suite;
- · CISCO technologies and CISCO IOS;

Languages

Italian: Native proficiency

English: Full professional proficiency

Personal Interests

Publications

Peer-reviewed Journals

[1] ReTiF: A declarative real-time scheduling framework for POSIX systems Gabriele Serra, Gabriele Ara, Pietro Fara, Tommaso Cucinotta *Journal of Systems Architecture* 118 (2021), p. 102210 DOI: 10.1016/j.sysarc.2021.102210

[2] A Framework for Comparative Evaluation of High-Performance Virtualized Networking Mechanisms Gabriele Ara, Leonardo Lai, Tommaso Cucinotta, Luca Abeni, Carlo Vitucci Cloud Computing and Services Science, 2021, Springer International Publishing DOI: 10.1007/987-3-030-72369-9 3

Peer-reviewed Conference and Workshop Proceedings

[1] An Architecture for Declarative Real-Time Scheduling on Linux Gabriele Serra, Gabriele Ara, Pietro Fara, Tommaso Cucinotta 2020 IEEE 23rd International Symposium on Real-Time Distributed Computing (ISORC), 2020 DOI: 10.1109/ISORC49007.2020.00013

[2] Comparative Evaluation of Kernel Bypass Mechanisms for High-performance Inter-container Communications

Gabriele Ara, Tommaso Cucinotta, Luca Abeni, Carlo Vitucci

Proceedings of the 10th International Conference on Cloud Computing and Services Science - Volume 1: CLOSER, 2020, SciTePress

DOI: 10.5220/0009321200440055

[3] On the Use of Kernel Bypass Mechanisms for High-Performance Inter-container Communications Gabriele Ara, Luca Abeni, Tommaso Cucinotta, Carlo Vitucci

High Performance Computing, 2019, Springer International Publishing

DOI: 10.1007/978-3-030-34356-9_1

Book Chapters

[1] Gabriele Ara,

Programmazione di App per Dispositivi con Sistema Operativo Android, Italian,

In: Manuale Cremonese di Informatica e Telecomunicazioni,

A cura di A. Liberatore et al.,

3rd Edition,

Zanichelli Editore (Italy), apr. 2020,

Cap. 33, pp. 1433-1486,

ISBN: 9788808920300.

[2] Gabriele Ara,

Programmazione di Applicazioni per Dispositivi Mobili, Italian,

In: Tecnologie e progettazione di Sistemi Informatici e di Telecomunicazioni,

A cura di Giorgio Meini e Fiorenzo Formichi,

2nd Edition, vol. 3.B.

Zanichelli Editore (Italy), apr. 2015,

Pp. 243-333,

ISBN: 9788808878809.

[3] Gabriele Ara,

Programmazione di App per Dispositivi con Sistema Operativo Android, Italian,

In: Manuale Cremonese di Informatica e Telecomunicazioni,

A cura di A. Liberatore et al.,

2nd Edition,

Zanichelli Editore (Italy), apr. 2015,

Cap. 35, pp. 1479-1509,

ISBN: 9788808151698.

[4] Gabriele Ara,

Programmazione di Applicazioni per Dispositivi Mobili, Italian, In: *Tecnologie e progettazione di Sistemi Informatici e di Telecomunicazioni*, A cura di Giorgio Meini e Fiorenzo Formichi, 1st Edition, vol. 3.B, Zanichelli Editore (Italy), apr. 2014, Pp. 295–387, ISBN: 9788808735010.